China in nineteen eighty three was the version of China
that made its transformation into what it is today
so very remarkable
that's to say
it was poor and it was underdeveloped
its gdp per Capita was three hundred and two dollars
making for a ranking of one hundred
and sixty first in the world
below the central African Republic
Uganda and the comoros
this made the country rather unattractive as an
expansion market for multinational enterprises
the population was massive  sure
but it didn't have a whole lot more going for it
from the perspective of corporate executives
and ultimately
even if companies wanted to enter the Chinese market
for the longest time
they just simply couldn't
it was one of the most closed off economies in the world
it was a centrally planned socialist economy
incompatible with the capitalist ones from the west
and there were barely even diplomatic
relations with Europe and America
let alone economic ones
so it's no surprise that before the nineteen eighties
no western auto manufacturer had
entered the Chinese market
change started after Deng Xiaoping took power
he kicked off the process of economic reform
leading to the process of opening up
leading to the Chinese government inviting a
few western auto manufacturers to form joint
ventures with Chinese car companies
leading to the first Chinese made Volkswagen rolling
off the line in Shanghai in nineteen eighty three
this was fortuitous
vw had been cajoled into forming a joint venture
with the Shanghai automotive industry corporation
and it happened at the absolute perfect moment
the same economic reforms that made it possible for vw
to enter the market kicked off the transformation
into the middle income behemoth China is today
and as disposable incomes grew and
the Chinese middle class expanded
so too did the country's car sales
since then  more so than any western auto company
vw has thrived on China sales  in fact
by the early two thousands
the country accounted for half of their global profit
it was the group's single largest market
manufacturing costs were cheap
sales were numerous
and profit margins were enormous
at least until recently
for decades  total sales in China were rising
while the group's market share largely held steady
in twenty nineteen
sales hit nearly four million units
but then the bottom fell out
covid can explain these years  sure
but not these ones
as vw has struggled to hit three million unit sales
and in the first three quarters of twenty twenty four
only mustered two million
across the thirty nine VW group factories in China
earnings are down about fifty percent
from the high set in twenty fifteen
while it's looking even worse for
certain brands within the group
Skoda a Czech automaker owned by VW since nineteen
ninety one has watched its sales absolutely tank
across the twenty twenties a disaster for a brand
that's tailored designs and even entire models
specifically to appeal to the Chinese consumer
but what makes this a true crisis for the world's largest
auto company is that things are bad beyond China too
this factory in Brussels  Belgium has been
building volkswagens since the nineteen
fifties and audis since two thousand six
but now  on account of slumping Audi q8 e Tron sales
vw has announced the factory will close its doors
at the end of February twenty twenty five
without a viable buyer for the factory
thousands of jobs are set to Vanish entirely
it likely won't be the last plant to close either
as Volkswagen announced that it would also
potentially close three additional factories
within Germany in an attempt at massive overhaul
something the company has simply
never done in its home country
all this the massive slump in sales
the unprecedented response to right size and stabilize
and the developing domestic distrust coming from it
has seen the group's c suite shuffled
German factory workers on strike
and pundits declaring this as potentially the
beginning of the end of Volkswagen's global dominance
but perhaps most concerningly
there's reason to believe that China is
just the canary in the coal mine
the graph speaks for itself
here's vw's market share in China
it's in free fall
and here's the market share of byd
China's newly minted automotive behemoth
back in twenty twenty
its market share sat at one point eight percent  today
it's at Eleven percent
making it not only the new largest auto company in China
but also the world's largest ev manufacturer
usurp ing even Tesla
BYD's explosive growth was spurred like many
things in China by a combination of central
planning and free market economics
around twenty twenty
Chinese governments of all levels  national
provincial and local
started rolling out a deluge of
incentives for evs and plug in hybrids
in Shanghai for example
the municipal government requires car buyers to
first purchase a license plate as a method of
restricting the number of cars hitting the road
these are sold via a monthly auction where
demand always far outstrips supply
only about five or six percent of
bidders typically get a plate
pushing prices up to between twelve
and fourteen thousand dollars
but for a number of years
ev buyers could get a license plate for free
an absolutely massive incentive considering some Chinese
evs now cost less than a license plate in Shanghai
there's also been a litany of buyer rebates
sales tax exemptions
infrastructure funding
direct support of automakers and more
that's totaled up to an estimated two hundred and thirty
billion dollars in funding for evs by the Chinese government
between two thousand nine and twenty twenty three
whereas elsewhere ev incentives were merely focused on
making them price competitive with internal combustion cars
in China they were often significantly cheaper
so it's no surprise their sales exploded
but of course
that just explains why China
transitioned to evs so quickly
not why BYD usurped vw
the explanation for that is that well
byd's cars were just simply better
in recent years
vw's entry level ev in the Chinese market was its id
three  which it was selling for about
twenty three thousand dollars
this model boasts a zero to fifty kilometer per
hour time of three seconds and a certified
range of four hundred and fifty kilometers
in the us or Europe
this would seem like a steal relative to other evs
but in China
for half that price
about eleven thousand eight hundred dollars
a buyer could instead get the upper
trim of the entry level byd ev
the seagull
this has a slower four point nine seconds
zero to fifty kilometer time and a shorter
four hundred and five kilometer range
but it's not too far off
and there are plenty of other buid evs selling for well
below the id three's price yet boasting better specs
the buid Dolphin night version has five
hundred and twenty kilometers of range
yet sells for under eighteen thousand dollars
for example
and the Volkswagen group isn't doing much better
on the other end of the Spectrum either
the group's two primary Luxury brands Audi
and Porsche are each struggling as well
Audi sold fewer than fifteen thousand evs to China
in the first nine months of twenty twenty four
and Porsche sales are in such free fall that the company is
closing a third of their dealerships in the country
there is a market for higher end western evs in China
but that market has been absolutely dominated by Tesla
the company convinced the government to allow them
to build their own dedicated factory in China
the first time ever a foreign auto company has been
allowed to enter the Chinese market outright
not as part of a joint venture with a Chinese firm
now western brands typically are able to
command a price premium in China
they're often viewed as luxury goods
vw doesn't necessarily need to beat its Chinese
competitors on price for equivalently spec'd cars
as historically consumers have perceived the
western brands as just simply better
until recently  that is
even if the id three or other vw evs might match or beat b y
d equivalents on range or acceleration or charging time
the day to day experience of owning a
vw ev is reportedly just worse
they lose in the details
and nowhere is that more true than with software
now  up until the twenty tens really
car manufacturing was largely an
exercise in industrial expertise
with companies like Toyota  Volkswagen and general
motors vying for the world number one spot in total
sales on account of their ability to produce durable
dependable  fixable hardware
then came Tesla
apple Carplay
Lane assist
heads up displays
and a myriad of other features running from safety to in
car entertainment that required cars capable of computing
suddenly  a software revolution
for legacy car makers such rapid change was jarring
but ultimately was such that they could at least
keep up with through outsourcing to smaller
more nimble software companies
making revolution more manageable too was the fact that
internal combustion engine cars simply don't require the
same level of software sophistication as an electric vehicle
a touchscreen infotainment system doesn't necessarily
need to interact with or be aware of a lane assist or
automatic braking safety feature for instance
so to keep up
Volkswagen at first went the route
of other legacy car makers
contract out the software
focus on their core competency
the hardware
but that changed in 2015 with dieselgate
the scandal involving an emissions control system designed
to fraudulently manipulate the results of emissions tests
as part of the ensuing legal settlement
the company invested two billion dollars
into building out the electrify America brand
of ev fast chargers in North America
and then forty billion dollars into their ev program
and as for the software that ran those evs and
their entire fleet of vehicles for that matter  well
vw was going to do that too
in twenty nineteen
the company announced that they no
longer look for software suppliers
but they'd be one
no longer would they mirror the
strategy of other legacy automakers
they'd take the Tesla route
they'd be a car company and a tech company
the vision was straightforward enough
they would radically simplify
and there would no longer be any black boxes that the
company itself couldn't understand under their hoods
each of their cars
leadership noted
were using some seventy separate computers
and across VW group's brands
there were eight separate software architectures
now the company wanted to cut those numbers to three
computers per car and one operating system across the entire
group
while the concept was simple the undertaking was massive as
VW group didn't even have a built out software branch so
they started from the ground floor founding a software and
technology company now called cariad here outside of Munich
at an Audi plant with a host of additional offices extending
as far as Seattle to house its three thousand new employees
now
no Volkswagen brand would have to rely on outside software
they'd have one in house operating
system serving their purposes alone
just as soon as they built it
this was a first
a legacy car manufacturer so boldly embracing software
GM hadn't made such a move
neither had Ford  nor Toyota
nor had Honda or Hyundai
neither had even Tesla
who shared the most similar approach to software
as Tesla from its founding was a software developer
making software a core competency from the beginning
but the problems were immediate
while Volkswagen was able to begin delivering
certain trims of its first modern electric vehicle
the id three in China and Europe nearly on time
the buyers were asked to patiently wait for
software updates before their infotainment systems
and heads up displays would be fully operational
1st paragraph for the company's first electric car
release in the much anticipated id series
it was a massive blunder
as Reddit and YouTube became rife with id three rants
and painful summaries of continued software snafus
making matters worse in the same year software
difficulties also delayed the release of the popular
vw golf as the company simply couldn't ensure network
safety in some markets for over the air updates
while the launch of the electric id four
in North America went a bit smoother
software soon proved the vehicle'sAchilles heel
as about a third of recall notices on the
vehicle could be attributed to software problems
unfortunately for the VW group
Koenigsegg's issues were more structural than
simply stumbling out of the starting blocks
issues for the ID group are largely attributed to
Koenigsegg's most rudimentary product e three one point one
the platform designed for the group's mass market evs
but卡里亚德in twenty nineteen was also tasked with
the concurrent development of two other platforms e three
one point two a step up in complexity designed for higher
end evs from the likes of Audi and Porsche as well as e
three two point zero a software product that would usher in
autonomous driving for the group in the late twenty twenties
cariad struggled with these products too
leading to delays on Porsche's ev Macan and
more recently Audi's q8 e Tron once again
on account of software
while Bentley counting on e three two point o to usher the
brand into its ev era has already announced that its full
transition away from internal combustion isn't likely until
the mid twenty thirties in part because of uncertainty over
whether造车can deliver a reliable product
from the beginning
起亚was founded to become a
central strength of the group
so it's been central in both near
and long term product roadmaps
and because it has failed so
spectacularly up until this point
it's left the entire group from mass market
to luxury in a state of uncertainty
now beyond the operational implications
the end result is still not what it needs to be
anecdotally
the reviews indicate that while VW
software might be improving
it's still far behind that of BYD or Tesla
so now the company is in damage limitation mode
along with the factory shutdowns
it's aiming to cut pay by ten percent across the board
and has already finalized a plan
to do so with managerial staff
largely through a reduction in bonuses
to avoid further factory closures and pay cuts though
the company needs to make some bold moves
it's starting by trying to find the next China
and vw believes one prime emerging
market opportunity is here in Brazil
this is in fact where VW opened its first international
factory in the nineteen fifties and today boasts four
factories  the company still believes there's
more juice to be squeezed
it's aiming for forty percent market growth by
twenty twenty seven by introducing fifteen new
electric and flex fuel models to Brazil
at the end of the day though
vw still thinks it can salvage the Chinese market
all they need to do is follow the
lead of the new market leaders
after plenty of public rhetoric on how they won't get
coked into a price war with the Chinese manufacturers
vw has been coked into a price war
with the Chinese manufacturers
and dropped prices across its
lineup to build back market share
recently  it also introduced the id code concept
a fully electric vehicle equipped
for fully autonomous driving
developed specifically for the
Chinese market with the kind of techy
futuristic features that have helped propel byd sales
this includes a self cleaning mode where the car
uses uv light to purify the air and a built in
robot vacuum cleaner to clean surfaces
VW also took a four point nine nine percent
ownership stake in Chinese ev startup xpeng
by collaborating with an established in market brand
Volkswagen says it will cut production time by thirty
percent and production costs by forty percent on the two
models it plans to introduce with xpeng in twenty twenty six
but ultimately
if VW evs are going to be competitive anywhere
they're going to have to get good at software
in July  Volkswagen announced a joint
venture with American EV Darling Rivian
known for breaching the SUV and
recreational vehicle markets
the initial one billion dollar investment will
be followed by another four point eight
billion dollars in the next several years
all dedicated to research and development and the
integration of Rivian software into Volkswagen
vehicles set to launch by twenty twenty seven
Rivian pioneered what's called Zonal architecture
basically splitting up a car's network to reduce wiring
and hardware and its interdependence on other systems
and the plans are to implement it first
into Volkswagen's Luxury brands
Porsche  Audi
and eventually down market to VW vehicles themselves
the transition towards electric vehicles has been a
difficult moment for the old guard of the auto industry
few would have predicted that a Silicon valley startup
could explode into the world's most valuable auto company
but then Tesla did
the incumbent manufacturers
eventually took this threat seriously
recognizing that it's now only a question of
how long the transition towards ev takes
not whether it'll happen
but suddenly byd has become effectively the second Tesla
the second ev manufacturer to achieve explosive growth
and unlike in the case of Tesla and the west
as byd rose
so too did a litany of other
smaller Chinese ev manufacturers
it's a far more diversified market than it was seen in the
us and Europe during the big growth years of Tesla
that's to say the challenge to the
incumbents this time is even stronger
perhaps the one upside for Volkswagen is that it's
having to confront this challenge now
Chinese ev manufacturers are just
starting to Ramp up exports
the cost of these evs is just so much lower
than competitors that they're sure to quickly
entrench in markets around the world
in response
the EU set tariffs that cut into this cost advantage
alleging that the prices are made possible
by significant government subsidies  the us
under similar logic
set a one hundred percent tariff
making it effectively impossible for Chinese
auto companies to compete in the market
but tariffs are not a wall
they're just a hurdle
and with time
the Chinese companies will find a way  already
byd is pivoting its Europe strategy to hybrids
as these are not covered by the tariffs
vw one could say has the opportunity to figure out how
to meaningfully compete against Chinese evs in China
before they have to do so across the globe
all the other auto companies without as significant a
China presence are not facing the same challenges
so they're not able to put their
products to the test in the same way
on the outside
evs look like cars
they are of course
and in many cases their bodies are
identical to those of gas powered equivalents
but what makes this industry transition
so tumultuous is that on the inside
the factors that influence competency in evs
design and manufacturing are so fundamentally different
than those that went into internal combustion cars
over a century of institutional knowledge within
companies like vw is now almost worthless perhaps the
biggest value they retain is just their brand
there's every reason to believe that successful
internal combustion vehicle manufacturers won't
turn into successful ev manufacturers
the task ahead for vw and other incumbent car manufacturers
is so tremendous that looking back in the decades to come
the ones that make it will perhaps be more
remarkable than the ones that don't
China is fascinating
i never get tired of trying to understand the
ways in which this nascent superpower is
increasingly affecting the entire world
and clearly
if you've made it to this point in the video
you're on the same page
that's why i'd recommend you watch
Polly matter's series China actually
it's an nebula original that attempts to dive
deep into how the country actually works
for example  you've heard about Chinese centrism
or their one child policy
or their elimination of poverty
and you probably remember the surface
level explanation for each of these
but do you really truly understand
each on a nitty gritty level
that's what China actually is for
it's a really interesting show
and this is just one example of Nebula
exclusive content that's worth watching
as you probably know by now Nebula is a streaming service
started by digital creators myself included designed from
the ground up to be the best home to video content
quite a lot of thinking has gone
into what that actually means
but it starts with the fact that it's
completely ad and sponsorship free
which means the way we make money on it is
through charging one low subscription fee
i know at first this sounds like a downside
but i believe it's the opposite
with this subscription fee
we're able to not only provide stable
predictable income to a curated
selection of top quality creators
we're also able to fund the production of top notch
higher budget nebula originals
the idea is that there are all these digital creators out
there that have great ideas about new things to make
they just need a little more money to do so
than what youtube's economics can support
this has produced shows like the getaway
a reality game show on wheels produced
by the wendover and jet lag team
or night of the Coconut
a film about an interdimensional
genocidal Coconut by Patrick Williams
and it really doesn't matter if you
still have no idea what that means
it's really good
you should really watch it
or boomers
a brand new doc by Tom Nicholas about how the baby boomer
generation managed to Amass so much wealth and power
and the consequences of this phenomenon
these are just a few of my favorites
but it's worth knowing that our twenty
twenty five nebula original calendar is the
busiest and highest budget it's ever been
making lots of really cool stuff
if you want to check nebula out
you can do so for forty percent off when you
head to our link nebula.tv/windover and using
that link will even help support the channel
so thanks in advance for your support